# **John Christian Gaby**

curriculum vitae

#### **Researcher Profile**

I study the composition and function of microbial communities associated with soils, plants, the gut, and anaerobic digestion systems. I apply molecular, microbiological, and bioinformatics methods including amplicon sequencing, metaGenomics, metaProteomics, enrichment and isolation, physiological characterization, and ecological statistics. I script in both UNIX and R for the analysis of massive datasets and the integration of multiple data types. In addition to my research activities, I have also trained graduate and undergraduate students and taught courses and workshops.

### **Contact Information**

**Phone**: +47 930 40 630 **Email**: john.gaby@nmbu.no

**Address**: The Norwegian University of Life Sciences (NMBU)

Institute of Chemistry, Biotechnology, and Food Science (IKBM)

P.O. Box 5003

1432 Ås Norway

## **Education**

**2013 Ph.D.** (Microbiology) Cornell University

**2002 B.S.** (Biology with emphasis in Microbiology) The University of Tennessee

# **Professional Experience**

2016 to present	Postdoctoral Researcher
	Department of Chemistry, Biotechnology, and Food Science, NMBU
2013-2016	Postdoctoral Researcher
	Biology Department, The Georgia Institute of Technology
2011-2012	Fulbright US Student Fellow
	Corporación Corpogen, Bogotá, Colombia
2006-2011	Graduate Research Assistant
	Department of Crop and Soil Sciences, Cornell University
2005-2006	Graduate Teaching Assistant
	Department of Microbiology, Cornell University
2002-2005	Peace Corps Volunteer
	United States Peace Corps, Ouallam, Niger
2002	Research Assistant
	Department of Microbiology, The University of Tennessee
2001	Howard Hughes Medical Institute Summer Research Fellow
	The University of Pittsburgh
2000	DOE Energy Research Undergraduate Laboratory Summer Fellow
	Biophysics Group, Life Sciences Division, Oak Ridge National Lab

## **Successful Applications**

Trained immunity and nutritional programming for resilient salmon, WP Leader for "Meta-omics and the gut microbiome-host axis", **HAVBRUK2**, 10.7 million NOK total award (2019).

Argentina CONICET Postdoctoral Research Fellowship (2012-2014, declined)

**Cross-Scale Biogeochemistry and Climate Small Grant** (2012)

**Fulbright U.S. Student Fellowship** to Colombia (2011-2012)

Biogeochemistry and Environmental Biocomplexity Small Grant (2010)

## **Supervisory Experience**

I have supervised the undergraduates Kyle Sexton (2014), Patrick Steck (2013-2015), Leo Zheng (2014-2015), Gabriel Ezuma (2014), Michael Blejwas (2014), Garrett Graham (2011), and Albert Chen (2010), and I have mentored and collaborated with the PhD students Lina Valderrama (2013-2015), Luz Medina (2014-2015), Silvia Greses (2016-2017), Kristin Herstad (2016-2017), Jane Ludvigsen (2017), Kine Svensson (2018), and Leszek Michalak (2017-2018), and the Master's students Thea Andersen (2018), Marius Strand (2018), and Isak Løfoll (2019).

# **Teaching Experience**

Amplicon Sequence Variant Calling with DADA2 in R workshop (NMBU, May 2018) Lecturer in Bioinformatics for Functional Metagenomics course (NMBU, 4-8 Sep. 2017) Teaching assistant for General Microbiology (Cornell, 2005-2006) ARB workshop, software for sequence database management (Corporación Corpogen, 2012) Quantitative, Real-time PCR workshop (The National University of Colombia, 2012)

### **Peer Review Service**

ISME, Frontiers in Microbiology, Applied and Environmental Microbiology, FEMS Microbiology Ecology, FEMS Microbiology Letters, Microbial Ecology, Environmental Microbiology Reports, PLoS ONE, Soil Biology and Biochemistry, Global Change Biology, and Soil Science.

### **Professional Society Membership**

International Society for Microbial Ecology (ISME)
Postdoctoral Member in the American Society for Microbiology (ASM)
Federation of European Microbiological Societies (FEMS)
Norwegian Biochemical Society (NBS)

#### **Publications**

Peer reviewed articles: 6 first author, 4 co-author

Book chapters: 1 first author.

- Svensson, R., Paruch, L., **Gaby, J.C.**, Linjordet, R. (2018) Feeding Frequency Influences Process Performance and Microbial Community Composition in Anaerobic Digesters Treating Steam Exploded Food Waste. Accepted Manuscript In Press, *Bioresource Technology*.
- Herstad, K.M.V., Moen, A., **Gaby, J.C.**, Moe, L., and Skancke, E. (2018) Characterization of the fecal and mucosa-associated microbiota in dogs with colorectal epithelial tumors. *PLoS One*.
- **Gaby, J.C.**, Rishishwar, L., Valderrama-Aguirre, L.C., Green, S., Valderrama-Aguirre, A., Jordan, I.K. and Kostka, J.E. (2018) A sequencing and analysis pipeline for *nifH* amplicons. *Appl and Environ Microbiol* 84 (4): e01512-17.
- **Gaby, J.C.**, Zamanzadeh, M., and Horn, S.J. (2017) The effect of temperature and retention time on methane production and microbial community composition in staged anaerobic digesters fed with food waste. *Biotechnol for Biofuels* 10: 302.
- Warren, M.J., Lin, X., **Gaby, J.C.**, Kretz, C.B., Kolton, M., Morton, P.L., Pett-Ridge, J., Weston, D.J., Schadt, C.W., Kostka, J.E., and Glass, J.B. (2017) Molybdenum-based diazotrophy in a *Sphagnum* peatland in northern Minnesota. *Appl Environ Microbiol* 83.
- Greses, S., **Gaby, J.C.**, Aguado, D., Ferrer, J., Seco, A., and Horn, S.J. (2017) Microbial community characterization during anaerobic digestion of *Scenedesmus* spp. under mesophilic and thermophilic conditions. *Algal Res* 27: 121–130.
- **Gaby, J.C.** and Buckley, D.H. (2017) The use of degenerate primers in qPCR analysis of functional genes can cause dramatic quantification bias as revealed by investigation of *nifH* primer performance. *Microb Ecol* 74: 701–708.
- **Gaby, J.C** and Buckley, D.H. (2015). Assessment of Nitrogenase Diversity in the Environment, p 209-216. *In* Bruijn, F.J. (ed), Biological Nitrogen Fixation, vol 1. John Wiley & Sons, Inc., Indianapolis, IN.
- **Gaby, J.C.** and Buckley, D. H. (2014). A comprehensive aligned *nifH* gene database: a multipurpose tool for studies of nitrogen-fixing bacteria. *Database: The Journal of Biological Databases and Curation*, 2014, bau001. doi:10.1093/database/bau001
- **Gaby, J.C.** and Buckley, D.H. (2012) A Comprehensive Evaluation of PCR Primers to Amplify the *nifH* gene of Nitrogenase. *PLoS ONE* **7**(7): e42149. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0042149
- **Gaby, J.C.** and Buckley, D.H. (2011) A global census of nitrogenase diversity. *Environ Microbiol* **13**: 1790-1799.

#### **Publications In Revision**

Karthikeyan, S., Rodriguez-R, L.M., Heritier-Robbins, P., Kim, M., Overholt, W.A., **Gaby, J.C.**, Hatt, J.K., Spain, J.C., Rosselló-Móra, R., Huettel, M., Kostka, J.E., Konstantinidis, K.T. *Macondimonas diazotrophica* gen. nov., sp. nov., a novel gammaproteobacterial genus dominating crude-oil contaminated sediments. In revision, ISME J.

#### **Publications In Review**

Wahid, R., Mulat, D.G., **Gaby, J.C.**, Horn, S.J. Effects of H<sub>2</sub>:CO<sub>2</sub> ratio and H<sub>2</sub> supply fluctuation on methane content and microbial community composition during *in-situ* biological biogas upgrading. In review, Biotechnology for Biofuels.

#### **Seminar Presentations**

- December 4, 2018. Dietary Mannan Selectively Enriches and Activates Microbes in the Cecum and Colon of Pigs. **3**<sup>Rd</sup> **International Metaproteomics Symposium**. Leipzig, Germany.
- November 20, 2018. In-depth analysis of shifts in microbial community composition and function with mannan diet. **Wood Prebiotics Exploring tree-derived hemicelluloses as a source for prebiotics**, Ås, Norway.
- November 13, 2018. A suite of molecular tools for ecological studies of nitrogen-fixing bacteria. **Nordic Enivronmental Nucleotide Network (NENUN)**, Copenhagen, Denmark.
- June 15, 2017. Multi-omic characterization of a commercial-scale, food-waste biogas reactor. **2**<sup>nd</sup> **International Metaproteomics Symposium**, Alghero, Italy.
- February 20, 2017. From microbiomes to productive, healthy crops: metagenomics to enable agricultural advances. **Norwegian Institute of Bioeconomy Research (NIBIO)**, Ås, Norway.
- January 20, 2017. Metabolic characteristics of 361 genomes recovered from the Oslo, EGE biogas reactor using shotgun metagenomics. **Norwegian Biochemical Society 2017 Contact Meeting**, Storefjell, Norway.
- September 26, 2016. Assessment of short vs. long read assemblies and their applicability to assessing microbial community dynamics and metabolism in a mesophilic biogas reactor. **Functional Metagenomics 2016 Conference**, Inderøy, Norway.
- October 23, 2015. From microbiomes to productive, healthy crops: metagenomics to enable agricultural advances. **University of California, Davis Department of Plant Pathology**. Davis, CA, USA.
- October 6, 2015. Molecular tools to study the diversity and ecology of nitrogen-fixing bacteria associated with crops. **University of Georgia Institute of Plant Breeding, Genetics & Genomics**. Athens, GA, USA.
- March 28-29, 2015. Diazotroph community dynamics in oil-contaminated sands of Pensacola Beach, Florida following the Deepwater Horizon oil spill. **Southeastern Biogeochemistry Symposium**. Atlanta, GA, USA.
- April 23-28, 2012. Microbial nitrogen cycling in a land-use series of the Colombian Paramo. **Fulbright U.S. Student Enhancement Seminar, Andean Region**. Quito, Ecuador.
- September 30, 2011. The diversity and ecology of free-living diazotrophs. **Corporacion Corpogen**. Bogota, Colombia.
- April 8, 2011. Diversity and ecology of asymbiotic nitrogen-fixing bacteria. **Cary Institute for Ecosystem Studies**. Millbrook, NY, USA.
- November 5, 2010. Assessment of quantitative, real-time PCR for enumeration of free-living diazotrophs reveals pitfalls of PCR-based methods. **Biogeochemistry and Environmental Biocomplexity Student Mini-symposium**. Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, USA.

- September 28, 2010. Quantitative, real-time PCR of the *nifH* functional genes (nitrogen fixation) using degenerate primers: how to avoid repetition of the same old PCR pitfalls. **Cornell Department of Microbiology**. Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, USA.
- April 2, 2009. Factors determining rates of N-fixation by free-living N fixers in soil. **Cary Institute for Ecosystem Studies**. Millbrook, NY, USA.
- October 2, 2009. Ecological study of a widespread but poorly characterized group of free-living, nitrogen-fixing bacteria. **Cornell Department of Microbiology**. Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, USA.
- January 4, 2008. Diversity of nitrogenase: current status of the census. **Cornell Department of Microbiology**. Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, USA.
- April 27, 2007. Anammox-related *Planctomycetes* in soil. **Cornell Department of Microbiology**. Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, USA.

#### **Poster Presentations**

- **Gaby JC**, L Michalak, L Lagos, S Leanti La Rosa, PB Pope, M Øverland, B Westereng. (August 12-17, 2018) Prebiotics for livestock: tree-derived galactoglucomannan alters the gut microbiology of weaning piglets. **ISME 2018 17**<sup>th</sup> **International Symposium on Microbial Ecology**. Leipzig, Germany.
- **Gaby JC**, S Greses, M Arntzen, D Aguado, J Ferrer, A Seco, and SJ Horn. (July 9-13, 2017) Metagenomic and Proteomic Analysis of Laboratory-scale, Mesophilic AnMBR and Thermophilic CSTR Biogas Reactors Receiving Microalgal Biomass Feedstock from a Photobioreactor Recovering Wastewater Effluent Nutrients. **Federation of European Microbiological Societies (FEMS)** 7<sup>th</sup> **Congress of European Microbiologists**. Valencia, Spain.
- **Gaby JC**, E Govasmark, LH Hagen, L Paruch, L Solli, PB Pope, and SJ Horn. (September 25-28, 2016) Assessment of short vs. long read assemblies and their applicability to assessing microbial community dynamics and metabolism in a mesophilic biogas reactor. **Functional Metagenomics 2016** conference. Inderøy, Norway.
- **Gaby JC**, M. Zamanzadeh, PB Pope, and SJ Horn. (August 21-26, 2016) Microbial community composition and dynamics in two-phase biogas rector systems. **ISME 2016 16**<sup>th</sup> **International Symposium on Microbial Ecology**. Montreal, Canada.
- **Gaby** JC, Overholt WA, and Kostka JE. (May 30-June 2, 2015) Diazotroph Diversity in Petroleum-Contaminated Sands of Pensacola Beach Following the Deepwater Horizon Oil Spill. **American Society for Microbiology 115th General Meeting**. New Orleans, LA, USA.
- Warren MJ, JC **Gaby**, X Lin, PL Morton, JE Kostka, JB Glass. (December 15-19, 2014) Interactions between nitrogen fixation and methane cycling in northern Minnesota peat bogs. **American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting**. San Francisco, CA, USA.
- **Gaby** JC, Kostka JE. (May 17-20, 2014) High-Throughput Analysis of Diazotroph Diversity in Marine, Wetland, and Agricultural Systems. **American Society for Microbiology 114th General Meeting**. Boston, MA, USA.
- **Gaby** JC, Steck P, Blejwas M, Jordan IK, Kostka JE. (April 5-6, 2014) A High-throughput Sequencing Pipeline for Characterization of Nitrogen-fixing Communities. **Southeastern Biogeochemistry Symposium**. Atlanta, GA, USA.

Hsu S-F, **Gaby** JC, and Buckley DH. (June 28-July 1, 2009) Exploring the links between the diazotrophic community and their function in soils. **15th Continuous Flow Isotope Ratio Mass Spectrometry Workshop**. Ithaca, NY, USA.

**Gaby** JC and Buckley DH. (June 1-5, 2008) The nitrogenase *nifH* gene: current status of the census. **American Society for Microbiology 108th General Meeting**. Boston, MA, USA.

# **Professional Development**

**Big Data and Machine Learning** course at Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences (Uppsala, Sweden, 2017)

Analysis of Multivariate Data from Ecology and Environmental Science, using PRIMER v6 (Orlando, FL, 2013)

MBL Microbial Diversity Course (Woods Hole, MA, 2007)

# **Language Proficiencies**

Spanish 4 semesters of university classes + 12 months immersion in Colombia French ACTFL Score of Advanced Low 2/7/2005

Zarma ACTFL Score of Superior 2/5/2005

English Native Speaker